<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>YIGIT ASIK, Data Scientist</title>
<link>https://yigitasik.github.io/#category=update</link>
<atom:link href="https://yigitasik.github.io/index-update.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Anything related to statistics, analytics, and data science</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 21:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Man on a Mission: January 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Yiğit Aşık</dc:creator>
  <link>https://yigitasik.github.io/posts/Man on a Mission - January 2025/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As I <a href="https://yigitasik.github.io/posts/Man%20on%20a%20Mission%20-%20Starting%202025/">promised at the start of the year</a>, here’s what I have studied this month.</p>
<hr>
<section id="statistics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="statistics">Statistics</h3>
<p>This month I finished <a href="https://allendowney.github.io/ThinkBayes2/"><em>Think Bayes</em></a> way before than I anticipated, and played with <a href="https://www.pymc.io/welcome.html">PyMC</a> a bit. I really enjoyed the whole book but wanted to dive a bit deep so moved on to John Kruschke’s <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/book/9780124058880/doing-bayesian-data-analysis#book-info"><em>Doing Bayesian Data Analysis</em></a> and I’m glad I did it. The book starts with main ideas of Bayesian view, <em>“Bayesian inference is reallocation of credibility across possibilities”</em> where credibility stands for probability and possibilities stand for possible values that our parameters can take when we attempt to model. After this introduction, Kruschke talks about what probabilities are and provides intuitive description for the distinction between <em>probability mass</em> and <em>probability density</em>. If you have trouble understanding probability distributions, you may want to take a look at it.</p>
<p>Bayesian stuff aside, I really enjoyed the interpretation of mean as minimized variance alongside how we end up with median and mode when we change the distance measure (e.g., l2 norm to l1 etc.). Also, I coded Metropolis Algorithm (1-D) by using the example in the MCMC chapter. You can find it on my GitHub under <em>learn-stats-with-sims</em>.</p>
<p>I’m currently at chapter 9, going through hierarchical models. We’ll see if the book keeps me engaged throughout the upcoming chapters as well.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="deep-learning-dl" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="deep-learning-dl">Deep Learning (DL)</h3>
<p>Well, I haven’t done much for the DL. Throughout the year, amount of time I spent on statistics will gradually decline to open up space for DL. I’ve just started to <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/hands-on-machine-learning/9781492032632/"><em>Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn, Keras, and TensorFlow</em></a>, skimming through Scikit-Learn part to start with Keras and Tensorflow while not missing out on anything (despite using sklearn pretty often, I don’t want to miss a useful thing that may come in handy in the future).</p>
<hr>
<p>In terms of sports analytics or production level data science, I haven’t done more than reading a few blog posts. Data science stuff aside, I have improved a lot on the website, added new functionalities such as widget to subscribe to the email list which allows you to get notified when I write a new post. It took quite some time to handle the front-end, so I count that as a win as well.</p>
<p>See you next month!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>update</category>
  <guid>https://yigitasik.github.io/posts/Man on a Mission - January 2025/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Man on a Mission: Starting 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Yiğit Aşık</dc:creator>
  <link>https://yigitasik.github.io/posts/Man on a Mission - Starting 2025/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="man-on-a-mission-series" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="man-on-a-mission-series">Man on a Mission Series</h2>
<p>Some time ago, I stumbled upon the website <a href="https://darrylblackport.com/"><em>Less Certainty, More Inquiry</em></a>. If you click on the link, you’ll see that Darryl Blackport shares what he listens to or reads every week of the year. I found the concept intriguing and thought it would be a great fit for me, as I’m often immersed in studying or reading something.</p>
<p>This year, I’m taking inspiration from his approach. I’ll share what I study each month, providing a brief overview of the topics I’ve explored, focusing on what I found particularly interesting or useful. To kick things off, here are my learning goals for 2025. Let’s dive in.<br>
<br>
<br>
</p>
<hr>
<section id="what-to-learn-in-2025-deep-learning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-to-learn-in-2025-deep-learning">What to Learn in 2025: Deep Learning</h3>
<p>For most of my data science journey, I’ve taken a theory-first approach, focusing heavily on statistics. However, with recent advancements in tools like LLMs, I think it’s time for a shift. In 2025, I plan to delve into deep learning (a domain I’ve avoided so far) with a hands-on approach.</p>
<p>Here’s my roadmap for deep learning:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/hands-on-machine-learning/9781492032632/"><em>Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn, Keras, and TensorFlow</em></a><br>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/advanced-learning-algorithms?specialization=machine-learning-introduction">Advanced Learning Algorithms</a><br>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/deep-learning">Deep Learning Specialization</a><br>
<br>
<br>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="what-to-learn-in-2025-sports-analytics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-to-learn-in-2025-sports-analytics">What to Learn in 2025: Sports Analytics</h3>
<p>I’ve been passionate about sports analytics for nearly a year now and have made significant strides in basketball analytics. (You can check out some of my work <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/yigitasik/">here</a>.)</p>
<p>This year, I aim to expand my focus by creating videos on football (soccer) analytics, in addition to basketball, on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@yigasIRL">YouTube channel</a>. To prepare for this, I’ve started the following specialization:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/sports-analytics">Sports Performance Analytics Specialization</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Also, Dean Oliver’s new book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Basketball-beyond-Paper-Analytics-Revolution/dp/1496240499"><em>Basketball Beyond Paper</em></a>, is on my reading list—it’s a must-read for anyone in this space.<br>
<br>
<br>
</p>
</section>
<section id="what-to-learn-in-2025-statistics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-to-learn-in-2025-statistics">What to Learn in 2025: Statistics</h3>
<p>I consider statistics to be one of my stronger skills compared to other data scientists in the industry (at least in Turkey), but there’s always room for growth.</p>
<p>Currently, I’m halfway through <a href="https://allendowney.github.io/ThinkBayes2/"><em>Think Bayes</em></a>, and I’m looking forward to Tom Faulkenberry’s <a href="https://www.routledge.com/Bayesian-Statistics-The-Basics/Faulkenberry/p/book/9781032744001">upcoming book</a> when it’s released.</p>
<p>There are specific topics, like meta-analysis, that I want to strengthen, but I don’t plan to tackle them systematically. Instead, I’ll explore them as curiosity strikes.<br>
<br>
<br>
</p>
</section>
<section id="what-to-learn-in-2025-production-level-data-science-maybe" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-to-learn-in-2025-production-level-data-science-maybe">What to Learn in 2025: Production-Level Data Science (Maybe)</h3>
<p>This one’s a “maybe.” Deep learning and LLMs are higher priorities, and the list is already packed. However, gaining production-level data science expertise could be beneficial in the long run.</p>
<p>For now, it’s something I’ll keep on the back burner, but we’ll see how the year unfolds.<br>
<br>
<br>
</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="a-final-note" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-final-note">A Final Note</h3>
<p>This blog post was polished with help of ChatGPT! I write the whole piece and feed it to ChatGPT to improve the flow.</p>
<p>And that’s pretty much it for my 2025 learning goals. Stay tuned for updates!</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>update</category>
  <guid>https://yigitasik.github.io/posts/Man on a Mission - Starting 2025/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
